To Saki, My Love
Episode Sixteen
To Saki, my love.
｢あなたが
この手紙を読むころには
By the time you read this letter, Mamoru and I are probably somewhere very far away.
私と守は どこか ずっと
遠い場所にいるはずです｣
I never would’ve thought I’d have to write such a farewell letter to my dearest friend and lover.
｢親友であり
恋人でもあった あなたに
まさか
こんな形で別れの手紙を
書かなければならないとは
思ってもみませんでした｣
I’m really, really sorry.
｢本当に 本当に
ごめんなさい｣
｢そして どうか
私たちを捜さないでください｣
Please don’t look for us, either.
｢書いてて なんだか本当に
妙に切ない気分です｣
Writing this makes me strangely sad.
｢守の置き手紙で
同じ文句を見たときには
I remember we were so angry when Mamoru left us a letter with these very same words.
私たちは
あんなに腹を立てていたのにね｣
｢でも 芸がありませんが
But I’m afraid my ineloquence forces me to resort to them.
私も同じことを
書くしかないようです｣
何もいらない
Nani mo iranai
I need nothing else
何もいらない
Nani mo iranai
I need nothing else
あなたがいればいい
Anata ga ireba ii
When you are by my side
あなたがいればいい
Anata ga ireba ii
When you are by my side
そっと横顔 息を殺す
Sotto yokogao iki wo korosu
I look at you in profile and hold my breath
そっと横顔 息を殺す
Sotto yokogao iki wo korosu
I look at you in profile and hold my breath
まばたきすれば消えてしまいそうで
Mabataki sureba kieteshimaisou de
I'm afraid it might vanish like an illusion if I blink now
まばたきすれば消えてしまいそうで
Mabataki sureba kieteshimaisou de
I'm afraid it might vanish like an illusion if I blink now
凝視めさせて好きだよ
Mitsumesasete suki da yo
Let me look at you, I love you
凝視めさせて好きだよ
Mitsumesasete suki da yo
Let me look at you, I love you
ああ 木々が震え 降り出した雪
Ah kigi ga furue furidashita yuki
The trees shake in the wind and snow gathers on the ground
ああ 木々が震え 降り出した雪
Ah kigi ga furue furidashita yuki
The trees shake in the wind and snow gathers on the ground
Harmony School
足跡 ふたつ 白く
Ashiato futatsu shiroku
Two lines of white footprints show
足跡 ふたつ 白く
Ashiato futatsu shiroku
Two lines of white footprints show
時よ 積もれ
Toki yo tsumore
Snowflakes of time, gather
時よ 積もれ
Toki yo tsumore
Snowflakes of time, gather
Harmony School
Entrance Ceremony
髪に 胸に ふたりだけの夢に
Kami ni mune ni futari dake no yume ni
In our hair, our hearts, our dream
髪に 胸に ふたりだけの夢に
Kami ni mune ni futari dake no yume ni
In our hair, our hearts, our dream
咲けない花の
Sakenai hana no
This flower cannot bloom
咲けない花の
Sakenai hana no
This flower cannot bloom
種は雪に抱かれ
Tane wa yuki ni dakare
And the snow embraces its seeds
種は雪に抱かれ
Tane wa yuki ni dakare
And the snow embraces its seeds
寄り添うの
Yorisou no
As they huddle together
寄り添うの
Yorisou no
As they huddle together
静かに忘れられたい
Shizuka ni wasureraretai
Quietly they wish to be able to forget
静かに忘れられたい
Shizuka ni wasureraretai
Quietly they wish to be able to forget
アハハハ… アハハ…
｢あなたが 私たちのことを
心配してくれることは
I’m really happy that you’re so
worried about us, and I empathize.
とても うれしいし
よく分かります｣
If our places had been reversed, I would be worried as well.
｢逆の立場だったら
私も あなたのように
心配することでしょう｣
｢ですが こうするしかないのです｣
There is no other way, however.
｢私たちは もはや神栖66町で
生きることはできません｣
We can no longer live in Kamisu’s 66th district.
｢町が 生きることを
許さないのです｣
The villages reject our existence.
｢私だけなら まだ
しばらく大丈夫かもしれません｣
Maybe I would have been able to stave it off for a while longer,
but Mamoru has already been branded with the mark of the disqualified.
｢でも 守は すでに失格の
らく印を押されてしまいました｣
｢一度 その らく印を押されると
There is no turning back once you are branded.
もう二度と元には戻れないのです｣
｢こんなの 人間じゃなくて
Don’t you think we are being treated more like defective products to be disposed of than like human beings?
不良品を選別するのと
同じやり方だと思わない？｣
｢焼き物の窯を開けたとき
Once the kiln is opened and the pottery inspected, all that are crooked or bear cracks are fated to be smashed.
いびつだったり
ひびが入ってたりした陶器は
打ち壊される運命にあります｣
｢私たちは このまま
打ち壊されるのを待つくらいなら
If all that awaited us was the fate of smashed pottery,
先に何が待っていようと
then we decided we would rather run away in the hopes of finding a different future.
逃げ出した方が ましだという
結論に達しました｣
｢本当なら
あなたと 一緒に行きたかった｣
To be honest, I would have gone with you.
｢これは 私の偽らざる気持ちです｣
That is my honest wish.
｢でも 早季は私たちとは違う｣
But you’re different from us.
｢前にも言いましたが
あなたは とても強い人です｣
I’ve told you before, but you’re very strong.
｢決して 肉体的にという
意味じゃないし
I don’t mean that in the sense of muscles,
気が強いとか
意志が強いというのでもない｣
nor do I mean that your spirit or your willpower is strong.
｢むしろ 涙もろいし
すぐに めげてしまう｣
Rather, you’re easily moved to tears and quickly discouraged.
I loved that part of you too.
｢私は そんなあなたも好きでした｣
But no matter what difficulties you face, and even if every fiber of your being is consumed by grief, you can recover.
｢でも あなたは
どんな困難に出会って
たとえ 心の底から
打ちひしがれたとしても
絶対に再起できる｣
You don’t completely succumb easily.
｢ぽっきりと折れてしまって
そのままという人じゃないんです｣
｢あなたなら
きっと 町で生きていけるし
I am convinced that you can live in
the villages and be a valuable asset.
町から必要とされるだろうと
思います｣
｢守は そうじゃない｣
The same doesn’t go for Mamoru.
｢そして 私が守を見放せば
Likewise, if I let him out of my sight, he will not live long.
彼は もう生きてはいけません｣
｢どうか 分かってください｣
Please understand.
｢町を離れてみて はっきりと
分かったことがあります｣
There is something I realized as we left the villages behind.
｢私たちの町は異常です
そうは思いませんか？｣
The villages are twisted.
Don’t you agree?
Can villages that kill their children to maintain peace and order be considered a normal human society?
｢町の安定と秩序を維持する為に
子供たちを殺し続ける町が
人間の社会として
まともでしょうか？｣
｢ミノシロモドキの話では
今の状態に至るまでに
According to the false minoshiro,
our history is one filled with bloodshed.
血みどろな歴史が
あったということでした｣
｢でも 今の町は
過去の どんな暗黒時代と比べても
However, I don’t believe we have much to be proud of
when comparing ourselves to the dark ages of the past.
自慢できるような
代物じゃないと思います｣
Looking back on what has happened in the villages, I now understand what twists it.
｢今 町で起きたことを
思い出してみると
その異常性が どこからくるのかも
だんだん見えてきました｣
It is the adults’ deep fear of all children.
｢それは 大人たちが心の底から
子供たちを怖れているという
事実です｣
｢もしかしたら いつの時代も
This has perhaps occurred in other times, too.
そういうことは
あったかもしれません｣
｢自分たちが創り上げたものを
It seems obvious to me that seeing the next generation tear down all you’ve labored to build would be difficult to accept.
後の世代によって
否定されるのは
不愉快なことに決まってますし
相手が血を分けた子供であれば
If they are related to you, it would be even harder.
なおさらに
辛いこともあったでしょう｣
｢でも 神栖66町の大人たちが
自分の子供たちに向ける視線は
The way the adults of Kamisu’s 66th district
look at their children, however, is different yet.
そうした感情とも違う
ちょっと異様なものです｣
It’s abnormal.
｢例えて言えば
Metaphorically speaking, one could say they are watching rows of eggs close to hatching.
ずらりと並んだ卵が
ふ化するのを待ちながら
中から出てくるのが天使なのか
A million eggs soon hatch into angels,
while one of them hatches into a demon.
それとも100万に１つの割合で
生まれてくる悪魔なのかを
額に脂汗を浮かべながら
じっと見守っているような
They watch the eggs tensely, cold sweat gathering on their foreheads.
Asahina
Satoru
Amano
Reiko
Itou
Mamoru
私たちは 何となく嫌な予感がする
というだけの理由で
Purely on the basis of intuition and premonition, hundreds upon thousands of eggs are smashed and discarded.
Inaba
Ryou
Katayama
Satoshi
Kawamata
Risa
割られ 捨てられてしまう
何百何千もの卵の
１個になることだけは
願い下げです｣
I refuse to join their ranks.
｢生まれ育った家を離れて
When I made up my mind that leaving the home I had been born and raised in was inevitable,
両親とも別れなければならないと
決意した時
本当に悲しく寂しい思いで
いっぱいでした｣
I was very sad and unhappy.
But when I thought about what everyone there truly felt, it gave me pause.
｢でも 向こうは 本当はどういう
気持ちだったのかを考えると
よく分からなくなってきます｣
Asahina
Satoru
Amano
Reiko
Itou
Mamoru
If I had been eliminated and disposed of by the villages,
｢もし 私が町から処分されると
決まったら
両親は さんざん泣いて
then, after much grief and tears, my parents would’ve eventually forgotten about me.
そして
最後には忘れることでしょう｣
Just as your parents eventually
accepted the fate of your sister.
｢あなたのご両親が
最終的に あなたの
お姉さんのことを諦めたように｣
I am convinced that our relationship is different.
｢私たちの絆は きっと
そうじゃないと信じています｣
｢もし
私が処分されることになったら
If I was going to be disposed of,
I know you wouldn’t leave me to die.
あなたなら
絶対 私を見捨てないでしょう？｣
｢あなたに危機が迫ったときには
If you were in danger, Satoru or I would do everything in our power to save you.
私や覚は どんなことをしたって
救おうとするはずです｣
｢私たちには
もう１人 友達がいました｣
We had another friend.
We are not allowed to even remember his name.
｢今は 名前を思い出すことも
許されない友が｣
X, as we call him, would have come to our aid too, right?
｢彼 Ｘも
そんなときは きっと私たちを
助けてくれたんじゃ
ないでしょうか？｣
｢だから 私は今
守を助けなくてはなりません｣
That’s why I have to help Mamoru now.
｢でも あなたや覚に
会えなくなることが
Being separated from you and Satoru is more painful than anything.
何より辛いのです｣
｢私たちには 幸い
呪力という万能の道具があり
Luckily, we have Cantus, an incredibly versatile power,
and can probably survive even if cast out into the wilderness.
自然の中に放り出されても
なんとか
生きていくことができるはずです｣
｢曲がりなりにも 呪力を
Being able to use my Cantus is the one thing for
which I am grateful to the villages and Sage Academy.
使いこなせるようになったという
点だけは
｢町と全人学級に対して
深く感謝しています｣
｢私と守は
これから２人で助け合って
Mamoru and I will now help each other and build up a new way of life.
新しい生活を築いていきます｣
｢そこで
あなたにお願いがあります｣
To that end, I have something to ask of you.
｢もし 町から私たちの消息を
聞かれたなら
If the people from the villages ask you
about us, please tell them we have died.
私たちは死んだと
報告してほしいのです｣
We are planning on going far enough to escape the eyes of the villages,
｢絶対に町の目が届かないくらい
ずっと遠くへ行くつもりですが
それでも 町が
私たちのことを忘れてくれたら
but if it helps them forget about our existence, it would help me sleep a lot easier at night.
今より多少は安心して
眠れるような気がするのです｣
いつか また 早季たちに
会える日が来る事を
I hope, from the bottom of my heart, that there will come a day when we will meet again.
心の底から願っています｣
From Maria, with love.
二度と真理亜には
会えないという予感は
The feeling that I would never see Maria again quickly turned into conviction.
なぜか確信へと変わっていた
Where did you get this letter?
この手紙 どこで？
どこで２人と別れたんだ？
Where did you part with them?
In… the… igloo…
あの かまくらの… とこで…
かまくら？
The igloo?
野狐丸
Yakomaru.
なんでございましょう？
Yes?
俺たちは 真理亜と守は死んだと
町に報告する
We will report to the villages that Maria and Mamoru have died.
口裏を合わせてほしいんだ
We’d like to get our stories straight.
Of course.
かしこまりました
どうか野狐丸めに お任せください
You can trust your servant Yakomaru.
Are you sure?
ホントに いいのか？
倫理委員会への
裏切り行為になるけど…
The Ethics Committee will consider this treason.
神様の仰せとあらば
何を迷う理由がございましょう
How could I not obey the command of a god?
お２方とも 雪崩に巻き込まれて
I believe it would be best to report that an avalanche plunged them down a ravine.
谷底に転落したということに
すれば よろしいかと思います
どこまで流されたか
分かりませんので
Since none know how far they fell,
searching for the remains would be difficult.
ご遺体の捜索は困難でしょう
工作には
多少の時間がかかりますが
It will take some time, but I believe that convincing bones could be arranged.
うまくいけば
お骨も用意できるかもしれません
それを届ければ
多分 ご納得いただけるかと
They will most likely understand if presented those.
どういうことだ？ 骨って
Bones? What’s going on?
Where are you going to get them?!
どっから
持ってくるつもりなんだ！
いえ そんな
とんでもございません 誤解です！
No, no, you misunderstand.
Of course there is no possibility that I would obtain the bones of gods!
もちろん 神様のお骨の調達など
できようはずもないでは
ありませんか
こんなことを申し上げるのは
大変 不敬と存じますが
I realize it insults you that I should say so, but portions of our skeletons cannot be reliably told apart from yours.
私どもの骨でも 部位によっては
神様のものと見分けが
付かないことがございます
とりわけ長身の者であれば
The tall ones of our race are similar in height to a young god.
若神様とは大きさも
さほど変わりません ですので
We will carefully chafe their bones with stones—
その骨を
念入りに石で擦りまして…
That’s enough.
もういい…
分かった！ あなたに任せるわ
I get it!
Do what you want.
かしこまりました
Very well.
どうか すべては
私 野狐丸めに お任せください
Please leave it all to your servant Yakomaru.
You look tired.
だいぶ お疲れのご様子です
このようなお誘いは
大変失礼かと存じますが
I know that my invitation must be rude, but would you like to spend the night at our colony?
よろしければ 我がコロニーで
お泊まりになられては
いかがでしょうか？
なにせ汚い所にて
そのような所に お誘いするのは
It shames me to invite you from one foul place to another.
大変 恐縮なのですが…
However, it is late now.
ただ なにしろ
この時間でございます
日が暮れてからの捜索は
危険を伴いますし
Any more searching at night will be dangerous.
ここは ひとまず
お休みになった方が
I believe it would be better to rest for the time being.
よろしいかと存じますが…
かまくらが無くなっていたのを
見たとき
When we saw that the igloo had vanished, we
immediately set out for the Robber Fly colony.
私たちは塩谷虻コロニーを
目指すことにした
唯一の手がかりである
スクォンクを発見するには
We felt that in order to find our only lead, Squonk,
the assistance of other queerats would help greatly.
同じバケネズミの力を借りるのが
早道だと思ったからだ
Of course we did not fully trust Yakomaru,
野狐丸のことは 決して心から
信じていたわけではないのだが
危急の際なので
but since it was an emergency, we were determined to use all means available.
利用できるものは
何でも利用しようという
気持ちだったのだ
だが 結果的に
まんまと利用されたのは
However, ultimately, we were the ones being used.
私たちの方だった
Manipulating some children blinded by haste was
likely child’s play for the sly and cunning queerats.
こうかつ極まりない
バケネズミにとって
焦りで周りが見えなくなっている
子供たちを操ることなど
児戯に等しかったのだろう
富子さんとの約束で
As the next day was the time limit that Tomiko-san had given,
明日中には 町に帰らなくては
ならないことを考えると
真理亜たちを発見して
連れ帰るのは
finding Maria and Mamoru and bringing them back seemed a hopeless task.
もはや絶望的だった
２人で併走しているという
事実を認識した時に
When I noticed that the two of us were skiing side-by-side, I realized what I had truly been afraid of.
私は 自分が本当に
怖れていたものの
正体に気がついた
My world consisted only of Sage Academy, if one excludes my parents.
私の世界は 両親を除けば
全人学級しかない
そして その中で本当に
仲間と言えるのは
And within that world, I could only call those of Group One my friends.
１班のみんなだけなのだ
それなのに その仲間たちは
次々と消えていき
One by one those friends disappeared, until only Satoru and I were left.
残されたのは
私と覚 ２人っきりである
嫌だ
I hated it.
I didn’t want to lose any more friends and loved ones.
もう これ以上
大切な人 愛する人を失うの
この世界で 私たちは
たった２人っきりなのだ
The two of us were alone in this world.
俺が操船するから
早季は少し休んでろよ
I’ll steer the boats.
You rest a bit.
どうして？
覚だって疲れてるでしょう？
Why?
You must be tired too.
いいから
Just rest.
Thanks.
ありがとう
どうすれば
真理亜を見つけられるの？
How can I find Maria?
I don’t understand.
分からない どうすればいいの？
What should I do?
教えて お願い
Tell me! I’m begging you!
私は 一体 何をすればいいの？
Just what should I do?
ウソよ… 何 言ってるの？
No…
Don’t say that…
That’s so cruel…
そんな ひどい…
Saki…
早季… 早季！
Saki!
早季 悪い夢でも見てたのか？
Saki.
Having nightmares?
うん ちょっと…
Yeah…
着いたよ
We’re there.
We have to use the snow shoes for a while again, though.
ここからは
また長板で行くしかないけど
早季は ここで待ってる？
Do you want to wait here?
私も行く
I’ll come with you.
そうか 分かった
Okay.
Got it.
早季 泣かないで
Don’t cry, Saki.
俺たち やれるだけのことは
やったんだから
We did all we could.
We still have a lot of time tomorrow, too.
それに 期限は
まだ明日いっぱいある
Let’s try the northwest tomorrow after dawn.
夜が明けたら
北西に向かってみよう
もしかしたら
真理亜たちの残した跡が
Maybe we’ll find some of their tracks there.
見つかるかもしれない
だから
どこまで信ぴょう性があるのか
That’s why I want to capture a false minoshiro and see how much of it is credible.
ミノシロモドキを捕まえたら
確認してみたいんだよ
こんな大きなパワーを持つ呪力が
Isn’t it obvious that something as powerful as Cantus
脳内でブドウ糖を代謝した
ちょっとのエネルギーで
can’t be powered by the tiny amount of energy released when glucose is metabolized?
まかなわれてるはずがないのは
明らかだろう？
The author wondered where Cantus comes from.
だったら その力は
どこから来るのか？ ってことに
なるけど
He suggested two hypotheses.
著者は
２つの仮説を紹介してるんだ
１つは 太陽系の中で
発動される呪力は
The first is that all Cantus used in the Solar System traces back to the Sun.
全て太陽に由来するって考え方
もう１つの説は…
The second hypotheses—
ねえ 覚？
うん 何？
Hey, Satoru.
Yeah?
私たち 真理亜や守のことも
忘れちゃうのかな？
Will we forget about Maria and Mamoru too?
たとえ 死んだって忘れないよ
Not even if I’m dead.
でも もし 教育委員会が
また私たちの記憶を…
But if the Board of Education alters our memo—
もう ２度とそんなことはさせない
I won’t let them do it again!
アイツらが いつまでも
They’ve got it wrong if they think they can
control my thoughts and memories forever.
意識や記憶まで管理できると
思ってるなら大間違いだ
もし 俺たちの意思に反して
強行しようとするなら
If they try to force something on
us again, we’re leaving the villages.
町を出るだけのことだよ
俺たちって？
We?
早季も 一緒に来てくれるだろ？
You’re coming with me, aren’t you?
全然 逆だからね それ
The opposite will happen.
The opposite?
逆？
I’ll leave the villages, and you’ll follow me.
私が町を出るの
それに覚が くっついて来るのよ
Fine.
分かったよ
それでいい
That’s okay.
ねえ もし 私たちも
町を出ることになったら
Hey, if we leave the villages too, let’s look
for Maria and Mamoru and live with them.
今度こそ真理亜たちを捜し出して
合流しよう？
ああ もちろん
Of course.
２人より４人の方が心強いもんな
Four are better than two.
そうよ！
その時こそ真理亜たちと 一緒に…
Yes!
And then, when we’re with Maria and Mamoru…
頭の中では 顔のない少年が
夢で言った言葉が
What the faceless boy had said in my dream continued to haunt me.
グルグルと回っていた
Why did he tell me what he did?
彼は なぜ あんなメッセージを
伝えてきたのだろうか
彼は 私に真理亜の逃走を
He told me not to aid Maria and Mamoru in their escape.
手助けしてはいけないと
言ったのだ
そして 彼女は
He also said that she had to die.
死ななくてはならないとも
Nakisou na aoringo kakaeteru mune no oku
泣きそうな青リンゴ  抱えてる胸の奥
In my chest, I carry a green apple that wets my eyes
Korogatte tsuyogatte
転がって  強がって
I fall over yet pretend to be strong
Kyuukutsu na sora niramu
窮屈な空睨む
I glower at the sky and it seems to suffocate me
Unmei ni juujun ni
運命に従順に
Do I look like I'd wait quietly
Jukusu no wo matsu mon ka
熟すのを待つもんか
For destiny to ripen it?
Sen no kaze
千の風
The winds
Agaite sakende
あがいて  叫んで
I struggle and scream
Fuke fuke
吹け吹け
Blow and blow
Watashi wa shabondama
わたしはしゃぼん玉
I'm a soap bubble
Soredemo shinjiteru
それでも信じてる
And still I have faith
Yokisenu arashi ni
予期せぬ  嵐に
In a sudden storm
Joushou shite kakou shite
上昇して  下降して
I rise and fall
Aragau shabondama
あらがうしゃぼん玉
I fight, soap bubble that I am
Soredemo ikiteku
それでも生きてく
And still I live on
Hajikeru shunkan niji hanate
弾ける瞬間  虹、放て
I make a rainbow when I burst
Department of Exospecies Control
237年の７月
In the year 237, in July,
Department of Exospecies Control
私は26歳になっていた
I turned 26.
You’ve got visitors, Saki-chan!
早季ちゃん お客さんだよ！
I’ll be right there!
は～い すぐ行きます